A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Logistical Services, Office Files of Robert Williams FA1718
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Logistical Services, Office Files of Robert Williams
1956-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Williams, Robert V.
Ford Foundation
FA1718
1.45 Cubic Feet 3 Hollinger boxes and 1 oversize photograph box
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files of Robert Williams who occupied different records management related positions in the Ford Foundation's Logistical Services unit between 1969 and 1974. Logistical Services operated within the Foundation's Division of Administration, and Williams was hired as a Records Analyst before becoming Records Services Manager. The collection consists of one series of subject files. Williams' staff subject files include a lot of material that originated from before he joined the Foundation and some material that appears to have been created by Robert Mayer who was Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services. This material may have been collected by Williams or may have been mixed in with his subject files at some point by the Foundation's archives.
The collection documents the development of the Ford Foundation's records management and archives policies and procedures. It contains correspondence, memos, drafts, reports, and notes that discuss topics like the Foundation's grants index, catalogued reports, information retrieval policies, filing procedures impacting the Foundation's field offices, records security, space allocation for records in the Ford Foundation New York City Headquarters building, microfilming, and data processing. In addition to documenting the activities of Williams and Mayer, the collection also contains a significant amount of memos and other records created by Margaret Sloane who was the Information Services Manager.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:098.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series of subject files.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1956-1980
Biographical / Historical
Robert V. Williams (1938-2017) was an archivist, information services professional, and educator. He worked in various records management and archives positions in the Ford Foundation's Logistical Services unit.
Williams received an undergraduate degree in Social Sciences and Education from Harding University in 1961, a Master's Degree in Library Science from Florida State University in 1964, and a PhD in Information Studies from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1978. Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, he worked at the Georgia Department of Archives and History from between 1965 and 1969. He became a professor at the University of South Carolina in 1978 and served as Director of the Office of Research for the College of Mass Communications and Information Studies between 2002 and 2004.
Ford Foundation; Archives; Information retrieval; Information services; Information storage and retrieval systems; Records -- Management
- Subject files, 1956-1980; 1; 1.45 Cubic Feet About 3 LTR size Hollinger boxes and 1 21x17 oversize photograph box (short)
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files of Robert Williams. The files document the Ford Foundation's evolving records management policies and procedures from the 1950s to the 1970s. They include correspondence, memos, reports, drafts, and notes that regard the Logistical Services unit's involvement in activities like the Foundation's grant index, catalogued reports, information retrieval policies and storage and handling equipment, filing procedures impacting the Foundation's field offices, records security, space allocation for records in the Ford Foundation New York City Headquarters building, vendors' bids for microfilming services, and data processing. The records show the Foundation's efforts to understand and address records management issues and the Logistical Services staff's efforts to learn, devise, and structure records management policies, procedures, and systems. In addition to documenting the activities of Williams, the series strongly highlights the work of Logistical Services Officer-in-Charge Robert Mayer and Information Services Manager Margaret Sloane.
  It is unclear if all of the files in the series were created and organized by Robert Williams or if some were mixed in with his subject files at a later point in time. Some may be closely associated with the staff subject files of Robert Mayer. A note from 1980 was discovered at the front of the series that is most likely not related to the work of Williams.
  - Sandra J. Markham note, 1980 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manpower Services - Files for individual grant awardees, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manpower Services Records Survey, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, outgoing, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous memoranda, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reports Control Center, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Vital records protection, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Historical evaluation of Ford Foundation reports, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Records Services - General, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Records Storage Center - General, 1966-1971; File contains architectural drawings. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - confidential material.
    Drawings in the file are Ford Foundation New York City Headquarters building plans of records storage space.
  - Micrographics Enterprises, Inc., Robert Marcelle, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Leasco Information Products, Inc., Dale Gripman, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vital records protection, 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A Plan for the Ford Foundation Information Center, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interoffice staff memoranda, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Archives inventory, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Records Services - Reports control, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Archives proposal, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Procedure Manual for Ford Foundation Grantees, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Overseas Representatives' Meeting, Nairobi, Kenya, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Automobiles purchasing, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Ford Foundation Mail and Communication Operations, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Administration: Problems, Plans, and Projects, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Records Services, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Records Management trip to overseas offices, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Resource redeployment study, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Records Services IR (information retrieval) units, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Foundation files, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Study of the Records Management Practices in the Ford Foundation, 1964 September (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Naremco Services Inc., 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Data processing, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Information Services questionnaire, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 32)